# TIMOTHY J. MURPHY

410.302.9996 | tim@followtim.com | www.followtim.com | LinkedIn

## **OVERVIEW**

Solutions-oriented IT Leader with a passion for integrating disruptive new technologies to enhance existing processes and drive key business objectives. Possesses wide range of advanced technical acumen including full stack development, machine learning, and infrastructure architecture. Influential software specialist who leads innovation and development in cloud-based security and disaster recovery solutions.

IT Governance | Full Stack Development | Project Management | Team Leadership Computer Networking | Cybersecurity | Research Design | Data Analysis | Data Modeling Machine Learning | Business Strategy | System Development | Process Innovation

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

PROSPERITY NOW 2017 – Present **Director of IT** 

Lead development on technology stacks to usher in new business and effective process workflows for NPO dedicated to providing financial solutions to limited-income households. Provide hands-on expertise to resolve security conflicts, manage firewall operations, and update networks. Identify opportunities for technical growth in collaboration with senior leadership and executive team.

- Enhanced company safety and reduced time on system reparations by establishing 3 year strategic vision for infrastructure and technology services.
- Liberated time to prioritize mission-driven projects to IT personnel by shifting entire infrastructure from private data center to cloud-based SaaS and IaaS solutions.
- Streamlined financial operations by replacing budgeting tool and transitioning General Ledger to SaaS system.
- Supported mission success through latest machine learning modeling techniques to effectively test predictive models.
- Secured organization with cutting-edge cybersecurity frameworks and postures.

A.I. SOLUTIONS 2014 – 2017

#### Technical Lead, IT

Directed high-performing IT team on application and technology design, and OS / hardware platform development. Handled technical infrastructure hosted at HQ, multiple remote sites, and the public cloud at multiple major providers. Conducted array of IT functions including user support and system deployments.

#### Responsibilities:

- Provided supplementary assistance to 450+ users nationwide in direct support of NASA, Air Force, and Army DoD contracts.
- Served as integral member of moving team for a.i. solutions headquarters office, supporting senior leadership on new technologies, facility design, and construction oversight.
- Drove business development for cybersecurity-focused government contracts, writing winning proposals based on different security frameworks including NIST 800.
- Developed and maintained strategic vendor relationships, conducting DAR analysis on services, equipment, and products to identify best-fit partnership for enterprise.
- Met ISO9001 requirements by deploying changes to internal Node.js application tracking purchasing request.

#### IT Project Management:

- Modernized Space Network's ground communication systems by using python and modern techniques to streamline speed and volume requirements for NASA SCNS contract.
- Implemented rigorous overhaul of network resources to include firewall, switches, VPN, security appliances, and a wireless infrastructure with 802.1x certificate-based authenticity as lead architect.
- Deployed leading next-gen IPS to enhance protection against threats based on network traffic insights.

# A.I. SOLUTIONS | **Technical Lead, IT** (Continued)

- Consolidated 125+ servers to ESXi 6.0 with network and vSphere security, creating virtual and systematic barriers between infrastructure, production machines, and contractual data.
- Enhanced customer services by streamlining new ticket system to accurately track resource allocation and reduce support response time.
- Designed and implemented new disaster recovery site that reduced operational downtime from 2 weeks to less than 4 hours in the case of emergency.
- Streamlined business operations by implementing Active Director redundancy, split DNS, and a segregation of IP address spacing and assigning DHCP scopes to correct nodes.
- Improved system integrity by deploying and maintaining financial systems including test applications and database servers.
- Created new pathway plan integrating 13 systems into single login structure using cloud-based Identity and Access management solution.

CFED 2012 – 2014

## **Network & Systems Administrator**

Developed and deployed network improvements to internal infrastructure in support of customer service, IT, and backup operations. Migrated existing functions with new solutions to improve service quality to infrastructure.

- Provided assistance to 60+ users at any given time, responding promptly to all queries regarding hardware, software, and networking issues.
- Reduced RTO and RPO from 24+ house to 15 minutes by devising new budget that resulted in a new backup solution.
- Slashed overall print costs by 15% with improved SLA and uptime by negotiating new contracts with multiple vendors to replace existing print operations.

#### **UNITED STATES MARINE CORPS**

2004 - 2008

#### Manager

Oversaw numerous activities to guide units on operational safety and protocol including route and supply preparations, multi-field cross-training, and movement briefings.

- Managed fleet of high-grade military vehicles and equipment including oversight of all maintenance and protective outfitting.
- Maintained guard force protecting military equipment, personnel, and sensitive information with zero loss.

# **EDUCATION**

UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND, College Park, MD	
Bachelor of Science in Computer Networking & Security	2013
Bachelor of Art in Criminology & Criminal Justice	2011
Certifications	
GENERAL ASSEMBLY   Data Science	2019
GEORGE WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY   Full Stack Development Bootcamp	2017

#### TECHNICAL SKILLS

# **Development**

JavaScript | jQuery | Python | Node.js | Express | React.js | React Native | GIT | Github MongoDB | MySQL | Firebase | HTML | CSS | Bootstrap | Media Queries | APIs | JSON | REST | AJAX | JLI | Unit Test | D3 | Spyder | Scikit-learn | NLTK | Pandas | Java

## Infrastructure

vSphere | AWS | AZURE | Okta | Salesforce | EqualLogic | Nimble | Cisco | ASA | IOS | HPE | Exchange | Office365 | Deltek | Intune | Redhat Linux | MFA | Wireless | Windows 2008R2; 2012R2; 7; 8; 8.1; 10